Finding Aid for Joseph E. Kincaid Papers, 1967-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Joseph E. Kincaid Papers 1967-1999
Kincaid, Joseph E.
1 film reels
9 linear feet
2012135 Aa 2
Joseph E. Kincaid is a medical doctor and right to life advocate who is based in Kalamazoo, Michigan. The Joseph E. Kincaid Papers document his leadership in the local, state, and national right to life movement, with a particular focus on the issue of abortion. Closely documented in the Papers is Kincaid’s involvement with several organizations, including Kalamazoo Right to Life Committee, Michigan Citizens for Life, and Right to Life of Michigan, Inc.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Dr. Joseph E. Kincaid (donor no. 10802 ) in June 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Joseph E. Kincaid is a medical doctor and right to life advocate who is based in Kalamazoo, Michigan. He was president of the Kalamazoo Right to Life Committee and executive vice president of Right to Life of Michigan. He continues as executive vice president as of this date (2012).
The Joseph E. Kincaid Papers document his leadership in the local, state, and national right to life movement, with a particular focus on the issue of abortion. The Papers are arranged into three series: Right to Life, Judicial and Legal Advocacy, and Issues. The papers are important for their insight into the legal, economic, and social criticisms of abortion while also highlighting the interconnected relationship between local, state, and national efforts to advance the right to life cause.
Subjects:
Kincaid, Joseph E.; Abortion--Michigan.; Pro-life movement--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; Kalamazoo Right to Life Committee.; Michigan Citizens for Life.; Right to Life of Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.
- Right to Life
  The Right to Life series is organized into subseries based on years. Within each year, materials are categorized as either Administrative or Educational. Administrative documents have mixed origin and reflect activities from the Kalamazoo Right to Life Committee, the Michigan Citizens for Life organization, and the Right to Life of Michigan, Inc. Meeting minutes, internal correspondence, and financial statements are among the types of records in the yearly Administrative subseries. Educational materials contain clippings, publications, and medical opinion articles written by Kincaid. Certain years, such as 1978 and 1980, contain records from with other subseries designation, including the Michigan Citizens for Life Convention and the National Right to Life 3 Year Plan, respectively. This series reveals the decision making and thought process of key right to life organizations and members, including Kincaid. It is the largest and most comprehensive series of the collection.
  - 1967-1970, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - 1971
    - Administrative (Box 1)
    - Educational (Box 1)
  - 1972
    - Administrative (Box 1)
    - Educational, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Educational, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - 1973
    - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Educational, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - 1974
    - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Educational, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1975
    - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Educational, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - 1976
    - Administrative (Box 3)
    - Educational, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Educational, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - 1977
    - Administrative (Box 4)
    - Educational, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - 1978
    - Michigan Citizens for Life Convention (Box 4)
    - Administrative (Box 4)
    - Educational, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - 1979
    - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Educational, 8 folders (Box 5)
  - 1980
    - National Right to Life 3 Year Plan, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Educational, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - 1981
    - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Educational, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1982
    - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Educational, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1983
    - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Educational, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1984
    - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Educational, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - 1985
    - Administrative (Box 6)
    - Educational, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - 1986
    - Administrative (Box 7)
    - Educational (Box 7)
  - 1987
    - Administrative, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Educational (Box 7)
  - 1988
    - Administrative, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Educational (Box 7)
  - 1989
    - Administrative (Box 7)
    - Educational, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1990
    - Speaker's Manual (Box 7)
    - Speaker's Bureau Kit (Box 7)
    - Administrative and Educational, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1991
    - Administrative (Box 7)
    - Educational, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - 1992
    - Administrative (Box 8)
    - Educational (Box 8)
  - 1993
    - Administrative (Box 8)
    - Educational (Box 8)
  - 1994
    - Administrative (Box 8)
    - Educational (Box 8)
  - 1995
    - Administrative (Box 8)
    - Educational (Box 8)
  - 1996
    - Educational (Box 8)
  - 1997
    - Administrative (Box 8)
    - Educational (Box 8)
  - 1998
    - Administrative (Box 8)
    - Educational (Box 8)
  - 1999
    - Administrative (Box 8)
    - Educational (Box 8)
- Judicial and Legislative Advocacy
  The Judicial and Legal Advocacy series reflect the many court and legislative initiatives led by Kincaid and others in the statewide right to life movement. The series, mostly from the 1980's, is organized topically and then chronologically. Much of the documentation arose around the state of Michigan's referendum to publicly fund abortions, which Kincaid and pro-life organizations opposed and protested. Of particular note is the 1989 pro-abortion legal brief of the ACLU and Right to Life of Michigan's legal brief regarding the state legislature's Public Act 59 of 1987. The documents in this series are useful for their ability to illustrate the contested legal aspect of abortion.
  - Death and Dying Legislation 1977-1989 (scattered) (Box 8)
  - Public Funding of Abortions 1977-1983 (Box 8)
  - Congressional Regulation of Abortion 1977, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Medical Treatment Decision Act 1979, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Pro-Abortion Brief on Public Act 59 of 1987 1989 (Box 9)
  - RTLM Brief on Public Act 59 of 1987 1989 (Box 9)
  - Brief re: Doe v. Babcock 1989 (Box 9)
- Issues
  Topical files comprise the Issues series. Other issues central to the right to life movement in Michigan and nationwide include euthanasia, assisted suicide, and boycott of the Upjohn Company for its production of drugs that are used during an abortion. Examples of materials in this series are position papers, legislative bills from neighboring states, and an audio recording used for presentation about the effects of abortion on the unborn fetus.
  - Marriage and Family Newsletters, 1970-1976, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Hiltz Publishing Co.'s Abortion, How It Is, 1972 (Box 9)
  - Euthanasia 1973-1993 (scattered dates), 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Upjohn Company Boycott Information and Packet 1981-1985 (Box 9)
  - Right to Die a Natural Death 1982-1984 (Box 9)
  - Advocates for Better Care 1989 (Box 9)
  - Assisted Suicide 1992 (Box 9)
  - Psychological Aspects of Abortion undated (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous 1972-1987 (Box 9)
  - Motion picture: American Film Institute, Metropolitan Visual Products Corp.'s Right to Life, 1972